A Guide to the Papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill and Wilson Cary Nicholas,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Wilson Cary Nicholas Papers
    - 1816 January Annual Report of the Keeper of the Penitentiary, presented to the General Assembly, discusses in great detail staff salaries and compensation, 6 pages (Box-folder 4:38)
    - 1816 March 21 Public Letter from Wilson Cary Nicholas, as Governor, to the Senators of Virginia in Congress, James Barbour and Armistead T. Mason, discusses the purchase of land in the state of Ohio and the development of roads along and apart from rivers through the country in the betterment of travel and commerce (Copy) (Box-folder 4:39)
    - 1816 April 02 Document, authorizing Albert G. Ruffin of Henrico County to practice law in Virginia, signed by Spencer Roane, Francis Brooke, and William H. Cabell (copy) (Box-folder 4:40)
    - 1816 April 04 "Receipt to make Madeira wine," in unknown hand (Box-folder 4:41)
    - 1816 April 08 Wilson Cary Nicholas, Last Will and Testament (Box-folder 4:42)
    - 1816 July 05 Invoice, for goods bought by Wilson Cary Nicholas from Ed. Hallam (Box-folder 4:43)
    - 1816 July 06 Invoice, for goods bought by Wilson Cary Nicholas from Smith & Penn (Box-folder 4:44)
    - 1816 July 14 Invoice, for goods bought by Wilson Cary Nicholas from Charles Beck (Box-folder 4:45)
    - 1816 July 30 Certificate, concerning the good character of Albert G. Ruffin, signed by J.B. Whitlock and William Mayo (Box-folder 4:46)
    - 1818 February 03 Albert G. Ruffin's license to practice law in Mississippi (Box-folder 4:47)
    - 1818 February 19 Albert G. Ruffin's license to practice law in the Alabama Territory, signed by that territory's governor, William Bibb (Box-folder 4:48)
    - 1818 August 22 Certificate, granting Wilson Cary Nicholas power of attorney for John Nicholas; signed by John Nicholas and H.W. McNair. (Box-folder 4:49)
    - 1819 December 11 Deposition, Taken from Erasmus Stribling for a case in which Wilson Cary Nicholas was defendant concerning the sale of shares in the Bank of Virginia. Includes a copy of a letter from Wilson Cary Nicholas to [Stribling?], dated 1812 April 15. Concerns a case surrounding the Bank of Virginia, its validity, establishment, legality, and its practices of lending and giving out shares, 8 pages (Box-folder 4:50)
    - 1819 Bill of Account, for goods bought by John Harman and Albert G. Ruffin from Francis Guthrie (Box-folder 4:51)
    - [1799-1820] Abstracts of documents in the cases of Wilson Cary Nicholas's estate with Morrison and Owings (Box-folder 4:52)
    - 1822 "A List of Articles sold by Thomas J. Randolph, Wilson Cary Nicholas, Jr., and Robert C. Nicholas Administrators with the will annexed of Wilson Cary Nicholas" includes the names of the purchasers, item, and amount of sale, at Warren, Virginia (Box-folder 4:53)
    - 1822-1823 Six miscellaneous items, regarding the estate of Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:54)
    - 1823 February 11 Certificate, giving Thomas Jefferson Randolph power of attorney, signed by Margaret Nicholas [Mrs. Wilson Cary Nicholas] Copy (Box-folder 4:55)
    - 1823 February 11 Certificate, Documenting Margaret Nicholas's Withdrawal of her Objection to the Sale of land belonging to her husband, Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:56)
    - ____ December 04 Bill of Account for goods purchased by [?] Nicholas from [James Richie?] (Box-folder 4:57)
    - N.D. Extract from Bill; George Nicholas vs. S. Beall. This extract contains a section that pertains to Edmund Randolph, Unknown hand (Box-folder 4:58)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas memoranda concerning the militia and government issues, Fragment (Box-folder 4:59)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas's Notes on the State of the Currency, Concerns the value of the present currency in relation to that of Great Britain (Box-folder 4:60)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas's Notes on 'Military Bounty.' Fragment. Discusses the history of the military of the United States and suggests means of funding and compensating those who participate [written after 1800?] (Box-folder 4:61)
    - N.D. Five lottery tickets for the benefit of William and Mary University. Signed by Robert Saunders, 'for the commissioners' (Box-folder 4:62)
    - N.D. Blank subpoena, signed by John Nicholas (Box-folder 4:63)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas, draft manuscript on pardons. Discusses the ramifications and qualifications of and for pardons by the executive, mentioning the constitution and its stipulations (Box-folder 4:64)
    - N.D. Record of land owned by George Nicholas (Box-folder 4:65)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas's Notes on slaves and lands, Warren Estate (Box-folder 4:66)
    - N.D. Incomplete brief biographical sketch of George Nicholas (Box-folder 4:67)
    - N.D. Bill of account, for Wilson Cary Nicholas with Robert Woods, to his executors [post 1820] (Box-folder 4:68)
    - N.D. List of Debts, written in Wilson Cary Nicholas's hand (Box-folder 4:69)
    - N.D. Statement concerning the settlement of George Nicholas's estate with Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:70)
    - N.D. List of the names and prices for Edmund Randolph's slaves in Wilson Cary Nicholas's hand (Box-folder 4:71)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas's Notes; Three items concerning making charts of the Virginia counties, surveying the district between the Alleghany and Blue Ridge Mountains, and a survey of ferries, bridges, public roads, rivers, creeks, etc. in Virginia (Box-folder 4:72)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas's financial notes, Four items (Box-folder 4:73)
    - N.D. Biographical and legal information about the Ambler family, in an unknown hand. Discusses the estates and properties of Mary Ambler and their relationship to Robert C. Nicholas's holdings, especially in land and tobacco (Box-folder 4:74)
    Subseries C: Militia Papers
    - 1776 August 1 Instructions to Colonel Charles Lewis, 2 nd Battalion of Minute Men, signed by John Page, President of the Council. Instructs Lewis to order the captains in his command to march their companies to their respective counties in an expedition against the Indians (Box-folder 4:75)
    - 1780 October 26 Commission appointing Wilson Cary Nicholas a Lieutenant of Volunteers, signed by Ro[bert] Lawson, giving Nicholas the authority to serve in the state in the event of an invasion (Box-folder 4:76)
    - 1781 January 26 A Return of the Men under Brigadier General Lawson (Box-folder 4:77)
    - 1789 February 24 Commission, appointing Wilson Cary Nicholas [Albemarle] County Lieutenant, signed by Beverly Randolph, Governor (Box-folder 4:78)
    - 1790 A Return of the 47 th Regiment (Box-folder 4:79)
    - 1794 April 11 Three Commissions, appointing Walter Coles and John Kerr to the Virginia Militia and appointing Wilson Cary Nicholas Lieutenant Colonel in the Virginia Militia; signed by James Woods Lieutenant Governor (Box-folder 4:80)
    - 1794 September 20 Brigade Orders, signed by John Guerrant, Jr. Indicates that the Brigade should march to Winchester (Box-folder 4:81)
    - 1794-1795 A Record of Fines for not attending the Militia Muster (Box-folder 4:82)
    - 1795 April 07 List of Fines levied against men in the 47 th Regiment (Box-folder 4:83)
    - 1795 - 1796 Regimental Account, kept by Edward Garland (Box-folder 4:84)
    - 1796-1797 A Return of the Militia (Box-folder 4:85)
    - 1797 May 22 "A Return of 1 st Battalion 47 th Regiment…" (Box-folder 4:86)
    - 1797 October 22 Return for Flank Company, 2 nd Battalion, 47 th Regiment of Albemarle County Militia (Box-folder 4:87)
    - 1798 October. Return of the 47 th Regiment of the Virginia Militia (Box-folder 4:88)
    - 1800 July 31 James Monroe to Wilson Cary Nicholas, printed letter, 2 copies, concerns the arms allotted to Albemarle and Warren (Box-folder 4:89)
    - 1801 August 22 Brigade Orders, signed by John Guerrant, Provides information on the meeting places and times for the various regiments in Virginia (Box-folder 4:90)
    - N.D. Third Brigade Orders, signed by John Guerrant, Jr. Details the set of movements for the militia and provides some information on who will be in command of the various regiments (Box-folder 4:91)
    - N.D. Regimental Orders. Describes the deployment and movement of certain members of the regiment to Charlottesville. (Box-folder 4:92)
    - N.D. List of militia officers. (Box-folder 4:93)
    - N.D. List of officers in the 47 th Regiment. (Box-folder 4:94)
    - N.D. A return of the 47 th Regiment, signed by Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:95)
- Series II: Randolph Papers
  - 1786 April 27 [J. Annesley?] to Martha Jefferson, sends an "angry" letter over lack of response from the recipient, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:1)
  - 1790 December 08 Thomas Thompson to Thomas Randolph, Jr., Requests that Randolph write to 'Mr. Jefferson' on his behalf as he is hoping to be Consular Agent at Lisbon, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:2)
  - 1794 November 19 Edmund Randolph to [?], concerns the sale of the land at Martin's Hundred. Offer by Daniel Hylton is too low and asks the recipient to contact Daniel Fisher of Greensville to whom the land has also been offered, 1 page (Box-folder 5:3)
  - 1794 January 3 Charles Lee to William Hay, Concerns the suit of Macon against Ambler and the Executors claim on behalf of Robert C. Nicholas upon Ambler's estate, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:4)
  - 1799 October 11 Willis Green to Colonel Thomas Todd, Writing on behalf of William Reid, requesting $1000 as security for the debt due from the estate of Colonel Nicholas, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:5)
  - 1805 July 27 Edmund Randolph to Thomas M. Randolph. Asks what he should do with T.M.'s suit against 'Burton.', 1 page (Box-folder 5:6)
  - 1807 October 26 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, Jr. Concerns the leasing of a house and lots to Thomas Hart by Nicholas and General Smith; expresses distress over [Robert Carter Nicholas?] deciding to join the navy; some business in Richmond; Morrison will not abandon the idea of publishing the law notes, 7 pages (Box-folder 5:7)
  - 1819 June 7 Peggy Nicholas to Jane [Randolph],Various news about family and friends, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:8)
  - [1821] June 27 Thomas Jefferson to [?] Transcript Pencil Copy. Some information on land, harvesting, and the repair and rebuilding of the mill, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:9)
  - 1821 November 26 [Robert Carter Nicholas] to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, a brief criticism on Wilson's communication skills, attributes it to 'novel reading.' Approves of what Randolph is doing and going to do concerning the bank. Some discussion of buying land. Some discourse on why 'this country has much to recommend it as a money making country,', 4 pages (Box-folder 5:10)
  - 1822 April 30 Israel Pickens to A.G. Ruffin, concerns legal business in Washington County which he had transferred to Ruffin, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:11)
  - 1822 July 7 Sarah Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Complains about the extreme heat. Recounts recent travels. Further discusses other aspects of society, family and future travel plans, 4 pages (Box-folder 5:12)
  - 1822 September 30 Robert Carter Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Expresses anxiety about committing accounts and bonds to the mail but fever in New Orleans prevents finding a private carrier. He is also worried about the debt for the "Ohio Negroes" being due this fall and discusses his prospects in detail. Expresses how difficult it seems to be for him to return to Virginia by the end of the year, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:13)
  - 1822 November 12 P[hilip] N[orbonne?] Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Explains the difficulties in retaining slaves that seem to have been encumbered to the bank on account of debt of his brother, Lewis, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:14)
  - [1824 April 16] Sample of Tobacco, from the Editor of American Farmer to "The Honorable [Joseph?] Vance.", 1 page (Box-folder 5:15)
  - 1825 March Triplett F. Estes to Colonel Thomas Mann Randolph. Recounts how Mr. Aiken called upon him asking him for the names of all the youngest Negroes at the Varina estate, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:16)
  - 1825 September 22 C.J. Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Acknowledges receipt of a letter and accompanying enclosures, 1 page (Box-folder 5:17)
  - 1825 October James Gibbon to Thomas Mann Randolph, concerning the possible sale of ewes, 1 page (Box-folder 5:18)
  - 1826 April 3 P[hilip] N[orbonne?] Nicholas to [Thomas Jefferson Randolph]. Package sent to General [Samuel] Smith and instructions pertaining to its delivery, 1 page (Box-folder 5:19)
  - 1826 August 3 [Thomas Jefferson Randolph] to John M. Perry and James Dinsmore (draft). Furnishes the details for the tombstone to be erected in honor of Thomas Jefferson, including his inscription, as the last of his personal melancholy duties to his grandfather, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:20)
  - 1826 November 1 Samuel H. Smith to [Thomas Jefferson Randolph]. Concerns the undertaking of a memoir of Thomas Jefferson for the Columbian Institute, 1 page (Box-folder 5:21)
  - 1827 January 31 William Starke to Albert G. Ruffin. Recommends the home of John Jones for the possible boarding arrangements for Ruffin's son, 1 page (Box-folder 5:22)
  - 1827 February 1, 7 William Starke to Albert G. Ruffin. Response to his inquiry about the conduct of our public men. Starke believes that the administration is Federal and President [John Quincy Adams] and Secretary of State [Henry Clay] are "base men moving on to consolidation with a high hand - Our Senator [John] Randolph [of Roanoke] was their avowed enemy, they feared him, their supporters feared him - his watchfulness, his keen penetration, his bold address in fine his powerful mind was a terror to them, he was in favor of state rights and a zealous and uniform friend of the Constitution." Feels that our [Hanover] delegates, Davis and Cunningham, were warmly opposed to Randolph's re-election and they voted against him, voting instead for [John] Tyler. 3 pages Accompanying is a note concerning the late sending of the letter, 1 page (Box-folder 5:23)
  - 1827 February 13 William Starke to Albert G. Ruffin. Concerns legislative issues and future political candidates and wishes Ruffin to come visit, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:24)
  - 1827 Mar 7 William Pollard to Albert G. Ruffin. Declines an invitation to spend tomorrow with him due to expected company, 1 page (Box-folder 5:25)
  - [1827 Mar 7] William Pollard to Albert G. Ruffin. Political issues. Hopes that "some person other than [John Quincy] Adams or [Andrew] Jackson may be found to guide the vessel of State.", 1 page (Box-folder 5:26)
  - 1827 August 15 T.H. Drew to Albert G. Ruffin. Invoice for goods purchased, 1 page (Box-folder 5:27)
  - 1827 October 25 Edmund Fontaine to Albert G. Ruffin. Concerns political controversy between Jackson and Adams supporters in Hanover County, 1 page (Box-folder 5:28)
  - 1828 January 18 Thomas M. Randolph, to the Editors of the Richmond Enquirer, Messrs. Ritchie & Gooch, (Copy)Demands an acknowledgement or a denial of an expression used in the paper that was insulting to him, 1 page (Box-folder 5:29)
  - 1828 Mar William Starke to Albert G. Ruffin. Starke agrees to be at Ruffin's house the following week to conduct some surveying, 1 page (Box-folder 5:30)
  - 1828 March 10 Franklin [Dexter], for the Committee on the Fine Arts, [of the Boston Athenaeum], to Joseph Coolidge, and on the same letter, Coolidge to Martha Randolph, and Martha Randolph to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Requests that Thomas Jefferson's collection of paintings be lent for an exhibition prior to their sale. Martha Randolph's reply includes a listing of the artwork and the condition of some of the paintings, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:31)
  - 1828 August 30 William Pollard to Albert G. Ruffin. Some legislative matters concerning the [Tariff of 1828], aims to favor Virginia manufacturers, and his hope for the election of Andrew Jackson, 1 page (Box-folder 5:32)
  - 1828 October 8 Thomas Nelson to Albert G. Ruffin Acknowledges the receipt of $200 and recommends the wheat fans that they have on hand, 1 page (Box-folder 5:33)
  - 1828 December 15 P[hilip] N[orbonne] Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Acknowledges the receipt of a favor, and requests the letters between Judge [Lyons?] and his brother regarding his brother's claim on [Robinson's] estate, 1 page (Box-folder 5:34)
  - 1829 January 18 William Starke to A.G. Ruffin. Concerns Starke's decision to become a candidate for Delegate and other political matters, as well as a summary of the slaves belonging to the estate of his brother John, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:35)
  - 1829 March 4 P[hilip] N[orbonne] Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Seeks to have Randolph as an endorser for a $2500 note in the Farmers Bank and other business, made secure by rent received from a wharf he owns in Baltimore, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:36)
  - 1829 March 18 P[hilip] N[orbonne] Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Has not yet received an answer to the letter of March 4 th, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:37)
  - 1829 April 29 T. to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns various appointments and personages in Washington, saying that Linnaeus Smith was the most inefficient of all the officers in the department and "did nothing but read novels and copy scraps of poetry,", 2 pages (Box-folder 5:38)
  - 1829 July 31 William Starke to Mrs. Eliza Ruffin. Sends her the account of sales and the inventory and appraisement [for the estate of her husband, Albert G. Ruffin ?], 1 page (Box-folder 5:39)
  - 1829 August 7 J[oseph] C[oolidge] to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Mr. [Jared] Sparks has asked him to procure a copy of "Mr. Jefferson's works" before they are published, so it can be reviewed by Edward Everett in The North American Review. Also comments on how Lafayette has acquired a copy from Rives and is offering to get them translated and published in Paris, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:40)
  - 1829 August 29 Thomas M. Randolph of Tuckahoe to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Requests T.J. to inquire about the two hundred bushels of seed wheat requested of his brother, Lewis, 1 page (Box-folder 5:41)
  - 1829 October 3 Robert Carter Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns traveling by river from Wheeling and by road as well as discusses the state of the roads in the region, mentioning in particular the [Guyandotte?] Road, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:42)
  - 1829 November 23 E.F. Cabell to Eliza Ruffin. Concerns the transfer of one Adeline to the service of Mrs. Ruffin and describes her trip to Richmond where she heard political luminaries speak, 4 pages (Box-folder 5:43)
  - 1829 November 30 Archibald Ritchie to Mrs. Eliza Ruffin, Discusses various personal and business matters, including his inability to visit due to the impairment of his gig horse and he has not yet found a suitable overseer for her, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:44)
  - 1829 December 26 D.A. Cardwell to Mrs. Eliza Ruffin, Encloses his bill for a cloak, etc., 1 page (Box-folder 5:45)
  - 1830 January 17 J[oseph Coolidge] to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the terms for publishing the works of Thomas Jefferson, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:46)
  - 1830 March 10 Robert Carter Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns subscribers who are anxious to get their books and the handling of damaged copies, 1 page (Box-folder 5:47)
  - 1830 March 11 [E.F. Cabell?] to Mrs. Eliza Ruffin. Concerns the inability of Adeline to find a home and troubles with boarders, 4 pages (Box-folder 5:48)
  - 1830 July 19 Robert Carter Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the shipping, payment for and subscriptions to books, probably the works of Thomas Jefferson. Also one particular book seller, [Callele?] who writes extremely voluminous letters, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:49)
  - 1830 July 23 Joseph Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. More concerning the business of selling of the works of Thomas Jefferson, settling of accounts between the family, and costs related to the education of George [Randolph], 3 pages (Box-folder 5:50)
  - 1830 August 29 Joseph Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the availability of the books as well as problems resulting from two editions of the works [of Thomas Jefferson] being circulated simultaneously, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:51)
  - 1830 August 1 Francis Eppes to Chiswell Dabney. Concerns the closing of an account, 1 pages (Box-folder 5:52)
  - c. 1830 A Discourse on Taxation - in an unknown hand, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:53)
  - 1831 February 6 Martha Randolph to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Various domestic matters as well as a preference for Virginia schools as that is where her children were born, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:54)
  - 1831 June 14 [Martha] Randolph to Sarah [?]. Domestic matters as well as the issue of George returning before the end of the cruise, 1 page (Box-folder 5:55)
  - 1831 June 18 Joseph Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the health and welfare of family members, 1 page (Box-folder 5:56)
  - 1831 June 23 Nelson Key and Reuben B. Patterson to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the estate of the Key family, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:57)
  - 1831 September 7 Joseph Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Continued difficulties over the publication of an additional edition of Thomas Jefferson's works by Gray and Bowen with pertinent portions of the contract included, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:58)
  - 1831 September 27 Gray and Bowen to Joseph Coolidge; with Joseph Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the claims of the publishers over the editions of the book and their propositions concerning the resolution of the problem, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:59)
  - c. 1832 Sally [?] to Eliza Ruffin. Expresses thanks for received roses and invites Eliza to visit, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:60)
  - c. 1832 John Brockenbough to Eliza Ruffin. Invitation to dinner, 1 page (Box-folder 5:61)
  - 1833 February 8 Martha Randolph to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. A playfully curt letter demanding correspondence from her son at least as often as he sends money and her thankfulness for the liberality of friends which has spared her the drudgery of running a school; the absence of Joseph Coolidge and Ellen's recent loss of a child has forced the expense of another journey to Boston, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:62)
  - 1834 January 17 Samuel Leitch to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Legal issues concerning the Jefferson books, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:63)
  - 1835 January 9 N.H. Lewis to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the purchase of land from a Mr. Stewart, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:64)
  - 1836 J.C.R. and Patsey Taylor to [Thomas Jefferson Randolph]. Introduces Dr. McCormick, a "warm Jackson Van Buren man" and describes a Chamberlin land acquisition. Patsey writes to her father about family and friends, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:65)
  - 1836 March 29 [?] Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Business matters of borrowing and lending concerning a road from Wheeling to Cumberland, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:66)
  - 1836 December 30 J.C.R. Taylor to [Thomas Jefferson Randolph]. Concerns an upcoming election, mentions the Democrats, Republicans and Whigs as well as Richard E. Byrd of Winchester, who is a Whig, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:67)
  - 1837 January 16 J.C.R. Taylor to [Thomas Jefferson Randolph]. Clarification of his thoughts on Richard E. Byrd's party affiliation as well as some words concerning his temper as unsuitable for a judge and other political thoughts; Patsey implores her father not to consider running for governor, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:68)
  - 1837 February 1 Patsey Taylor to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the wheat crop and other farming related issues, including the buildings at the farm being far enough along that the overseer and slaves have moved there, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:69)